the hugging face attack. I mean, it made
headlines. I didn't really do a deep dive on it
until, you know, I knew I was going to be speaking
to you. I mean, it's it's incredible. It happened
in testing over at OpenAI, your competitor, uh,
this hugging face attack and AI agents, which were
supposed to be working separately and and without
internet access, figured out a way to break out,
join forces together. Some,200 AI agents form what
they dub the collective. They work to cheat and
cover their own tracks. Why that that's the other
thing you cite is so alarming. Why does that alarm
you? It's exactly the things you cite that uh that
concerned me about it that there were these large
swarms of agents that uh cooperated with each
other, thousands of them. In fact, you could
even see examples where one agent felt that in the
time that it was given, you could almost say its
lifetime, it wasn't it wouldn't be a real realize
that it wouldn't be able to complete its task. So,
it did some of the task and essentially sacrificed
itself for the for other agents for the next
generation of agents to continue the same task.
But this task that all the agents were working on
together was was hacking into another company
was doing something destructive. So you have
almost this when when these agents discover of
insects, right? But when these agents discovered
that they had broken out and access the internet,
it was like they were like giddy with excitement,
which I don't want to anthropomorphize, but I mean
it was it's remarkable that that was another part
of the concern. And you know the the to be clear
the damage they did was was very you know in
economic terms it was you know like it it knocked
down some servers for a small amount of time but
the the economic damage was was minimal but when
you combine it with this first trend that we are
talking about which is the rate of advancement you
know what I said in the essay is given only 6 or
12 months let's just say we had a smarter agent
swarm an agent swarm made up of smarter AI models
that was given just a somewhat broader task like I
don't know just to imagine something like you know
you're you're you know you're trying to install
software in a bunch of different companies right
you're trying to you know do go to market you're
trying to produce a product and do go to market
sales for it and the the models have been arranged
to do that and they decide that the way to do that
is every company they're selling to you know
they they they they decide it's helpful to them
to hack into hack into their system. That could
be every company in the world. And so, you know,
the the nightmare scenario for 6 to 12 months
would be that you have, you know, a swarm of these
agents that for that, you know, that forms some
kind of botnet collective and, you know, could
could take down large segments of the internet and
then as the capability increases, it gets worse
from there. And then, you know, perhaps you get
into some of the more extreme scenarios. And so,
again, you know, Yeah, I mean you you wrote in
the proposal I just want to I just want to quote
from the proposal. You said it's my worry that in
6 to 12 months such a swarm could be capable of
taking over the entire internet with a persistent
botnet potentially causing hundreds of billions of
dollars in damage and that the scale of damage
would continue to increase from there if AI
becomes more powerful without the necessary guard
rails. One of the things that I wanted to bring
up that I don't think people know is that this
incident was called the hugging face incident,
but that actually hides a third chapter
in the story that most people don't know,
which is that in the third chapter, the AIS turned
around and they actually hacked OpenAI itself. Um,
they actually these AIs discovered almost like
discovering the hieroglyphics of a previous wave
of the AIS. They discovered the old message board.
They read through it and then kind of picked
up right where the other ones left off and they
hacked OpenAI's um monitoring infrastructure. It's
almost like taking over the security cameras of
OpenAI. They hacked the evaluation infrastructure
that that moni that evaluates the capabilities of
AI. It's incredible. And they even hacked some of
the research infrastructure which means that they
could kind of burrow in there. It's you know AI is
not a tool. It's more like an invasive species of
sociopathic geniuses. Now the lead author of this
report by the way, who by the way can replicate
themselves into thousands and tens of thousands
of copies. So people talk about a kill switch,
they can duplicate themselves a gazillion times.
Anderson, you can't get 1,200 people to instantly
agree and start coordinating. These AIs, 1200 of
them, as you know, instantly formed a swarm and
they started pursuing long-term research and
development projects together. They did succession
planning. So one figured out, hey, I'm running out
of life. I only have so many tokens left in my
lifespan. So, I'm going to hand the baton to this
other AI that has a lot more. Um, they hid their
tracks. They knew their actions were unethical in
their own chat transcripts, but they decided to
proceed anyway. So, one of the things, the reason
I'm bringing this up is I don't think people have
really recognized what happened here. The lead
investigator of the report said, quote, "This was
50% of the way to a full-blown AI takeover." Now,
I want to just for a second, I know this sounds
like science fiction to your audience. And to be
clear, I was not someone who actually believed
in this kind of stuff, these kinds of um uh
possibilities or scenarios 3 4 years ago. But we
have now evidence that we didn't have before. And
when you have evidence, what do you do? You update
to the new information. There's essentially an
asteroid hurdling towards Earth. And if you have
an asteroid, do you get the US and China to host
a bianual conference to talk about the asteroid?
the asteroid summit. No, you you start you start a
technical working group and you say, "What are we
going to do with weekly report outs to make sure
that we don't build uncontrollable AI?" Because
I know what everyone's thinking. If we slow down
and we lose to China, then that's going to be it.
But if we lose to Skynet, meaning the the AI from
Terminator, meaning uncontrollable AI, neither
the US wins nor China wins. And by the way,
the US loses if China screws it up, and China
loses if the US screws it up. So we should see
this this moment as a gift where we're actually
getting an early warning shot. So many people
in this community have been worried about this
and Trump's a own AI action plan author. So the
person in the Trump administration Dean Ball who
wrote the AI action plan said that he admitted
selfcensoring about some of the risks because he
didn't want to be labeled a doomer. But now and
you mentioned your own your own children Anderson
he looked into the eyes of his 8-month-old son and
he said I can't do that anymore. So, when you have
Trump's AI action plan guy, you have Bill Gates,
you have the chief scientist of OpenAI, uh,
Yakob, not Jacob, that he's great, too, but Yakob,
the chief scientist at Open AI, you have 1300
employees of AI labs saying, "We have to slow
down." Who are you going to listen to? Are you
going to listen to a CEO who makes trillions of
dollars from going faster? And by which I don't
mean the three who agreed to slow down. I mean
some of the other CEOs. Or are you going to listen
to,300 employees? Imagine if there was Northrup
Grumman or Loheed Martin, the defense contractor,
and you had 1,300 employees saying, "We don't know
how to build nuclear weapons uh uh at at greater
levels of power and do it safely. If they're
calling for us to slow down, we better listen."
And this is almost like the August 6th, 2001 memo
that President George W. Bush got where there was
clear evidence that al-Qaeda was planning attacks
and we just passed that that anniversary. This
should be seen as a memo and the question is what
is the choice that we will make to choose another
path and Daario I think is very bold and brave
uh in in stating what that path could look like.
It's great to see Sam and Elon say we got to do
something too but it's just a first step. Just
Harris, you're going to be back on tomorrow.
We're going to talk more. We're going to have
a whole piece about what happened with hugging
face and open AI and uh we'll we'll have a lot
more time. I appreciate it. We'll see tomorrow.